<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A moderate ansvver to these two questions 1. Whether ther [sic] be sufficient ground in Scripture to warrant the conscience of a Christian to present his infants to the sacrament of baptism. 2. Whether it be not sinfull for a Christian to receiv [sic] the sacrament in a mixt assembly. Prepared for the resolution of a friend, and now presented to the publick view of all, for the satisfaction of them who desire to walk in the ancient and long-approved way of truth and holiness. By T.B. B.D.</title>
            <author>Blake, Thomas, 1597?-1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 104 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76816</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3148</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E19_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12103</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859207</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859207</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111276</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76816)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111276)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 4:E19[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A moderate ansvver to these two questions 1. Whether ther [sic] be sufficient ground in Scripture to warrant the conscience of a Christian to present his infants to the sacrament of baptism. 2. Whether it be not sinfull for a Christian to receiv [sic] the sacrament in a mixt assembly. Prepared for the resolution of a friend, and now presented to the publick view of all, for the satisfaction of them who desire to walk in the ancient and long-approved way of truth and holiness. By T.B. B.D.</title>
                  <author>Blake, Thomas, 1597?-1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I.N. for Abel Roper, at the signe of the Sunne over against S. Dunstans Church in Fleet-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645 [i.e. 1644]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>T.B. = Thomas Blake.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Novemb: 28. 1644.".</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Infant baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111276:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A MODERATE ANSWER To theſe two QVESTIONS
<list>
                  <item>1. Whether ther be ſufficient Ground in Scripture to warrant the Conſcience of a Chriſtian to preſent his Infants to the Sacrament of Baptiſm.</item>
                  <item>2. Whether it be not ſinfull for a Chriſtian to receiv the Sacrament in a mixt Aſſembly.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prepared for the Reſolution of a Friend,</hi> And now Preſented to the publick view of all, for the ſatisfaction of them who deſire to walk in the Ancient and long-approved way of Truth and Holineſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> T.B. <hi>B.D.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>EPH. 4. VER. 1.2.3.</hi>
               </bibl> I therfore, the Priſoner of the Lord, beſeech you that yee walk worthy of the Vocation wherwith ye are called: with all LOWLINES and MEEKNES, with long-ſuffering, forbearing one another in LOVE, endeavouring to keep the UNITY of the Spirit, in the Bond of PEACE.</q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>I.N.</hi> for <hi>Abel Roper,</hi> at the ſigne of the Sunne over againſt S. <hi>Dunſtans</hi> Church in Fleet-ſtreet, 1645.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:111276:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111276:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou deſire mine opinion touching theſe two Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether there be ſufficient Ground in the Scripture to warrant the conſcience of a Chriſtian to preſent his Infants to the Sacrament of Baptiſm, with an expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Benefit that may accrew unto them by it?</p>
            <p n="2">2 Whether it be not ſinfull for a Chriſtian to receive the Sacrament in a mixt Aſſembly? <hi>I ſhall endeavour to give Anſwer to them both for the ſatisfying of your conſcience. So that you turn not Conſcience into Will: and Iudgement into Affection.</hi> The meek <hi>(yea only the meek)</hi> will the Lord guid in judgement, and teach his w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y. The ſecret of the Lord is with them that fear him, he will ſhew them his Covenant, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.</p>
            <div n="1" type="answer">
               <head>The Anſwer to the firſt Queſtion.</head>
               <p>AS for the firſt, I anſwer affirmatively: There is ſufficient Ground in that Scripture to warrant the conſcience of a Chriſtian to preſent his Infants to the Sacrament of Baptiſm, with an expectation of Benefit that may accrew unto them by it: wherein I obſerve two particulars. 1. Whether the Parent ſo doing may be excuſed from ſinning through an unwarrantable uſe and Application of Gods Ordinance? 2. Whether he may in the uſe thereof expect any Benefit ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crewing to the Infant? Theſe two are different in their own Nature, and require either of them ſeverall Grounds of Satisfaction. For tho, if it be ſinfull for the Parent to bring his Infants to Baptiſm, he can expect no good for them by it: In as much as no man may expect good to come from what is evill: yet tho it be not ſinfull in the Parent, it will not follow that Good may be expected by it: But I hold the Affirmative part of Both to be the Truth of God.</p>
               <div n="1" type="argument">
                  <head>The firſt Argument.</head>
                  <p>This I build upon the words of our bleſſed Saviour in <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.14. <hi>Suffer little children, and forbid them not to come unto me</hi> — Children. The children
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:111276:3"/> here m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ntioned were <hi>Infants,</hi> ſuch as men do hold in their arms: The text ſaith <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that <hi>He took them up in his arms, &amp;c.</hi> Where we ſee that our Saviour was highly diſpleaſed with his Diſciples, who had rebuked the Parents for bringing their children to Chriſt. Hence I argue Chriſts juſtification of what is done doth preſuppoſe the lawfulneſſe of the thing. It was (therfore) lawfull for the Parents to bring their children to Chriſt to receiv his Bleſſing if lawfull for them, ſo alſo for others, for all. Conſequently even for us there is a ſufficient warrant to preſent our Infants to Chriſt, that they may receiv his bleſſing. You will reply: That, tho it be lawfull to preſent Infants to Chriſt to receiv his bleſſing, yet not (therfore) lawfull to preſent them to Baptiſm: I admit your reply but rejoin thus. If lawfull to preſent them to Chriſt for his bleſſing: Then lawfull to preſent them to him in his Ordinances in which that bleſſing is to be expected. This I ſuppoſe will ſtand good: That whoſoever might be welcom to Chriſt in his perſon, were he here upon earth may be admitted to his Ordinances in which he is preſent by the power of his Spirit. For who doubteth but that he hath ſet up his Ordinances in the Church for this end; that in them he might meet thoſe of his who deſire to draw neer unto Him: and by theſe Ordinances as by a Mean appointed for that end convey to them that Bleſſing and Grace, which were he preſent with us in the fleſh, he would beſtow upon them. This being laid down for a Ground: I build upon it thus: but ther is none other of Chriſts Ordinances, in which, and by which a Chriſtian can preſent his Infants to Chriſt, with expectation of his Bleſſing excepting this of Baptiſm: Conſequently, either by Baptiſm they may be preſented to Chriſt for his bleſſing, or not at all: If not at all: Either Chriſts preſence in his Ordinances is not equivalent to his Corporall preſence, or ſome prohibition hath in a ſpeciall maner put in a Barr to keep them off from his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances which did not keep them of from him when here upon earth: If any ſuch there be, let it be named: if not: Then is ther a ſufficient ground to warrant the Parents bringing their children to Chriſt in his Ordinances, and particularly in Baptiſm, that ther-in they may expect the Benefit of Chriſts Benediction.</p>
                  <p>I know what hath been objected: <hi>viz.</hi> That ther is a Barr to hinder Infants implyed in theſ texts: <hi>Math.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.16. <hi>Act.</hi> 8.36. from whence this Argument is framed: without Faith none may be baptiſed: Infants want Faith, and (therfore) They may not be baptiſed: And then, To what purpoſe ſhould they be preſented to that Sacrament. To which I anſwer: That granting the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption to be true, (tho if a man deny it as ſome do, <hi>Vide Greg. Decretal lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>De Baptiſmo &amp; ejus effectu,</hi> I ſee not how it can be proved): But I ſay, let it be granted that Infants have not Faith: The Propoſition is utterly falſ: <hi>viz.</hi> That without Faith none may be baptiſed: For neither do the texts prove it; and beſides, ther is good reaſon againſt it.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The texts prove it not: 1. Not <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. This indeed ſheweth what the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:111276:3"/> Miniſtery muſt do: Not what the People: The Miniſtery, muſt teach all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; But defineth nothing, whether they may not be baptiſed before they have learned, or before they do beleev: much leſs doth it ſay, None but beleevers may be baptized. 2. Nor <hi>Mar.</hi> 16. This text ſheweth, what is the iſſue of Beleeving, and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing Baptiſed, <hi>viz.</hi> That ſuch ſhall be ſaved: and contrarily, He that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth not ſhall be damned: But ſaith not, That none may be baptiſed who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeveth not. <hi>Ob.</hi> But the Order of the Words doth inferr it. Beleeving ſet before Baptiſing: <hi>Sol.</hi> I reply: That Doctrines collected from the order of words are not alway ſound, nor ſuch Arguments concluſive: <hi>Ex. gr. Mat.</hi> 3.6. <hi>they were baptiſed, confeſſing their ſinns.</hi> And <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Born again of water, and of the Spirit:</hi> Here is <hi>Baptiſed</hi> before <hi>Confeſſing:</hi> and <hi>Water</hi> before <hi>Spirit:</hi> yet doubtleſs they did confeſs their ſins before they were baptiſed: And who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not, that the Spirit doth ſometime prevent the Water of Baptiſm. 3. Nor yet <hi>Act.</hi> 8.36. This indeed proveth the affirmative, <hi>viz.</hi> That He who beleeveth may be b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ptiſed. But from thence to conclude the Negative, That He who beleeveth not, may not be baptiſed, is againſt all Rules of reaſoning: which will yet more plainly appear by this: <hi>Philip</hi> ſaith, <hi>If thou believe with thy whole heart, thou maiſt;</hi> Will any man thence conclude, That whoſo beleeveth not with <hi>his whole heart,</hi> may not be baptiſed? And ſo take liberty to barre all ſuch as preſenting themſelves, and profeſſing their faith, may yet perhaps juſtly be ſuſpected of Fiction and Diſſimulation? You ſee then, the texts do not prove the Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Nay, ſuppoſe that not by inference, but in direct terms, ſome of theſe texts ſhould ſay, He that beleeveth not, ſhall not be baptiſed: ought we not to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it as true only in thoſe perſons of whom the text ſpeaketh? <hi>viz.</hi> Of them that have been taught, and yet do frowardly refuſe, and profeſs a diſlike and misbeleef of what hath been taught them? And ſo it will be too weak an Argument, to prove that univerſall Propoſition, and much leſs to draw on the deſired concluſion, Without faith none may be baptiſed, None, <hi>Ergo,</hi> Not In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants: <hi>ex. gr.</hi> That text of <hi>Mark</hi> ſaith: <hi>He that beleeveth not ſhall be damned, q. d.</hi> Without Faith none ſhall be ſaved: Will any man underſtand this in that Univerſality as to include Infants? Will he aſſume Infants beleeve not, have no faith. (therfore) They ſhall not be ſaved? God forbid: The Propoſition hath it's latitude of Truth, beyond which it may not be extended. So then, theſe texts do ſhew what is required of the Apoſtles and their ſucceſſors: What of the Nations and Heads of the Families in the Nations, perſons that are <hi>Sui juris,</hi> not under the command of another: But determineth nothing of inferiours, and much leſs concludeth againſt Infants Baptiſm.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Good reaſon againſt it. For why? Firſt, a profeſſion of Faith is enough to entitle men to Baptiſm: Tho there be no ſoundneſs and ſincerity in the heart at all: Witneſs the admiſſion of <hi>Simon Magus.</hi> True indeed, except there be
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111276:4"/> ſoundnes in the heart, God may juſtly deny man the Benefit which otherwiſe he might expect. But, if he make profeſsion to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>leeve in Chriſt, who ſhall dare to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ny him the Sacrament. 2. That which is preſuppoſed to aſſert the neceſsitie of Fait<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>: (underſtanding it of the grace it ſelf, is doubtful, <hi>viz.</hi> That without Faith no man hath wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>with-all to r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ceiv the Benefit of Baptiſm. This I ſay may well be doubted, if not denyed: eſpecially if we intend to comprehend Infants and little child<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en: They have a paſſive capacity, which is enough to receive that Gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce and Benefit which we conceiv is reached forth to <hi>them</hi> in that Sacrament: And what is that? Not ſ ch a fulneſs of Grace, or the Habits ther-of, as may be expected by them who have formerly been prepared by the Diſcipline and infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Word: But rather <hi>initiall and ſeminall Grace,</hi> that ſeed of God, wher-of the Scripture ſpeaketh, <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.9. The which doth not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſe Grace in the Heart, but is it ſelf the ſeed and root of Faith, and all other actuall Graces whatſoever. To men and women converted by the Word, and then coming to Baptiſm, <hi>viz.</hi> To <hi>Criſpus, Cornelius, Lydia &amp;c.</hi> we beleev that Baptiſm doth (as to <hi>Abraham</hi> Circumciſion did) convey a ſuper-addition of further Grace to what they had formerly received in and by the Word: But to their children, Baptiſm conveyeth (as did Circumciſion to <hi>Jſaac</hi>) the beginning and firſt ſeeds of Grace; And conſequently calleth for no previous diſpoſitions and preparations in the Recipient: only a paſſive capacity not croſs-barred with obſtinacy and infidelity. It is the property of <hi>preventing</hi> Grace, to be the firſt mover in the Heart, and to make way for it's own Reception: Is this acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to be done in the miniſtry of the Word upon the Parents (as it is ſaid of <hi>Cornelius</hi> and <hi>Lydia</hi>) and ſhall it ſeem unreaſonable to grant it to be done by this firſt Sacrament in their children? For why? Did we conceiv the Spirit (who is the chief Agent and efficient working in and by the miniſtry of the Word and Sacraments, and with-out whoſe operation and aſſiſtance, they are but as empty veſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ls and edgleſs tools) the Spirit I ſay did we conceiv him working only as a morall Agent, to ſtand at the door and knock, as only ready and willing to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter if the door be opened; to proffer Grace, if man will receiv it; Then were it reaſon indeed to require Faith in Children no leſs than in their Parents: But it is not ſo: We conceiv him in the Baptiſing of Infants working as a Naturall or rather as a <hi>ſuper-naturall</hi> Agent, <hi>viz.</hi> opening the door and entring, putting Grace in the Heart, and working it in the Will, conferring upon them ſuch a Grace as for the preſent they are capable of, <hi>viz. initiall,</hi> and <hi>ſeminall,</hi> as before was ſaid.</p>
                  <p>Add this alſo: That in the Baptiſing of Infants, ther is not Baptiſm altogether without Faith. Ther is preſuppoſed the Faith of the Parent; And this ſufficeth to qualify the Infant for Baptiſm, yea, for the Grace and Benefit of that Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. What is the Benefit of Baptiſm? Is it not Remiſsion of ſin and ſpirituall
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:111276:4"/> Regeneration? To the obtaining of which, why may not the Faith of the Parent ſuffice? In the child, as yet corruption of Nature which he brought into the world is not active: it hath produced neither thoughts, words, nor deeds againſt the law: and therfore calleth for no perſonall Act of Grace to remove the Guilt ther-of. Guilty he is and polluted, but guilty only by i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>putation, and polluted, not by any conſent of his own, but by the act of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>viz.</hi> of his Parents<note n="*" place="margin">Quantò magis prohiberi non d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>het infàns, qui recens natus nihil peccavit, niſi quòd ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum Adam carnaliter na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus: qui adr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſſam peccato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum accipiendam hoc ipſo ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliis, acced t, quòd illi remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuntur non propria, ſid alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na peccata. <hi>Cyprian. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pla. 59.</hi>
                     </note>: Is it any wonder that the imputation of anothers faith, ſhould procure for him Remiſsion and removall of that which cometh by the imputation of anothers act? That as he ſinned in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo he may be ſaid to beleev in another? Here is then the equity of Gods proceedings; that what Malady and miſchief was contracted without his will, ſhall be cured and remedyed without him, and any act of his: It is by the ordinance and inſtitution of God that the guilt of <hi>Adams</hi> tranſgreſſion is imputed to the Infant, and the Corruption of Nature pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagated: And it is by the Ordinance of God, that the Guilt of that ſin is remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and a Remedy againſt that Native diſeaſe provided: and both theſe are done in and upon the Infant, without any concurrence of his own will. And as by the act of the Parents, corruption of Nature is propagated (their act it is, tho not voluntary in them) So by the act of the Parents (in this it is a voluntary act) by Faith laying hold upon the Promiſe of God in that Sacrament is obtained for the Infant, and beſtowed upon him the Grace of Regeneration: This to be the root and ſpring of future holines and righteouſnes, as the other was the root and ſpaun of wickednes and profaneſs. <hi>Ob.</hi> It is ſaid, That every man muſt live by his own faith, not by anothers. <hi>Sol.</hi> By <hi>his faith,</hi> indeed it is ſaid that the <hi>juſt ſhall live, Hab.</hi> 2.4. It is not ſaid, <hi>Not by anothers,</hi> this is not in the text of the Prophet; Nor doth the text ſpeak ſimply of the Benefit it ſelf gained by Faith, but of the Pre-aſſurance ther-of: No pre-aſſurance of Salvation but by Faith: But this doth not prove, That by his faith the Parent may not obtain for his child this benefit of Baptiſm, the Remedy for that Malady. We read in the Goſpell, That the woman of <hi>Canaan</hi> obtained mercy for her daughter: The man for his luna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick ſonn, the Centurion for his ſervant, the friends and neighbours for the Palſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick man. Which inſtances have been alleged by Divines to manifeſt this point in hand, <hi>viz.</hi> The Benefit of Baptiſm obtained for the child by the Faith of the Parents.<note place="margin">Bernard Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m. <hi>66.</hi> in Cantica. Ecbertus contra Cathacos, Serm. <hi>7.</hi> Remigius <hi>on</hi> Mat. <hi>15.21.</hi> Calvin: Harmon <hi>on</hi> Màt. <hi>9.</hi>
                     </note> That note of <hi>Remi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius</hi> is worth the noting. She ſaith not, Help my daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but <hi>help me, and have mercy on me:</hi> and ſo <hi>Mar.</hi> 9.21. The father of the Lunatick ſaith, <hi>If thou canſt do any thing have compaſſion on us, and help us.</hi> He puts himſelf in as a Co-partner of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111276:5"/> his childs miſery, Say the ſame here. It is a mercy to the Father that he can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail for his child; who if he do rightly underſtand himſelf ſuffereth in his child: yea, not only by the way of compaſſion, but as feeling the ſmart and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of himſelf: And therfore hath need to ſue unto God for the Removing of that puniſhm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt which lyeth upon himſelf, in his child. Yea, he hath this reaſon to ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llenge it at the hand of God by the prayer of Faith, that ſo he may obtain the fulnes of the Promiſe made to the faithful in the Covenant of Grace. Infants are part of their Parents; So that the promiſe of Grace mentioned in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant betwixt God and the Faithfull. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. is not ratified to the whole Parent, except alſo it do extend to his Infants. So then, it is the Faith of the Parent laying hold on the Promiſe which qualifieth his Infant for the Grace and good effect of Baptiſm.</p>
                  <p>Nay yet more: This text on which the Argument was grounded, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19. cometh yet neerer to the point; For firſt, the bleſſing of Chriſt which the Parents ſought and found for their children, was not terminated in an externall and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Benefit, as per-adventure it might be replyed touching thoſe former In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances: Doubtleſs the Bleſſing of Chriſt extended to the good of their ſouls; and yet procured by the Faith of the Parents without any concurrence of Faith in the Infants. I will not per-emptorily affirm it: But probable enough it is, that theſe Parents having been by <hi>Johns</hi> Baptiſm directed to Chriſt, when they knew him, brought their children to Him to receiv a further bleſſing from him, even that which <hi>John</hi> told them he could not give, but they muſt expect it from another, even from Chriſt. Next it may be worth the noting: That our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Suffer little children to come unto mee.</hi> To come, not, To be brought; The act of the Parent is reputed the act of the child: That none may deride the ſaying of the Ancient, <hi>Credit in alio ſicut peccavit in alio,</hi> He beleeveth and cometh to Chriſt in and by his Parent, as formerly he had ſinned in the loins of another.</p>
                  <p>Corollary: To conclude this firſt Argument, Since by that text of our Bleſſed Saviour, we have ground to believ, That Infants preſented to him are accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; Since, what perſons might be brought to him, may be preſented to his Ordinance; There being no barr put in by any word of Chriſt to keep them of. Nay more, Since the Faith of the Parent doth lay hold upon the promiſe of Grace not only for himſelf, but for his Infants; yea ther is ground to believ the imputation of the Parents faith to the Infant; I conclude ther is ſufficient ground in Scripture to warrant Parents to preſent their Infants to this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and that with expectation to obtain the Grace and Benefit of the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="argument">
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:111276:5"/>
                  <head>The ſecond Argument.</head>
                  <p>THis I ground upon the words of our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.0. A charge given to the Apoſtles to inſtruct the Nations, whom they ſhould convert to the Faith, to inſtruct them (I ſay) in the obſervation of all ſuch Ordinances as Chriſt had commended to them. This Obſervation enjoyned hath ſpeciall reference to mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Diſcipline for the right Ordering and Government of the Churches and Aſſemblies of Chriſtians: in which he inſtructed his Apoſtles no leſſe than in matters of Faith and Doctrine, as it is evident out of <hi>Act.</hi> 1.2. where is mention made of ſome Commandements which Chriſt gave to his Apoſtles touching things pertaining to the kingdom of God. And it is no leſs evident by ſome paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages in the New Teſtament, <hi>ex: gr. Cor.</hi> 11.2. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.15. &amp; 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2. that ſome things were delivered to the Churches, and particularly to the Miniſters ther-of which were not then committed to writing, but delivered from Hand to Hand, called therfore <hi>Traditions.</hi> Theſe were not matters of Doctrine, eſpecially not Articles of Faith (None ſuch do we acknowledge but what are delivered and ſet down in the writings of the Holy Apoſtles and Evangeliſts) But matters of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, and Rules of good order in the Church. Theſe Ordinances ſett up and practiſed by th'appointment of the Apoſtles, are equivalent in Authority to what Chriſt himſelf hath immediatly ordained. Hence that of St. <hi>Paul, Cor.</hi> 14.37. Conſequently a Ground on which Conſcience may build, and therby may aſſure it ſelf that ther-in it doth not ſinn againſt God. Of the which we cannot doubt, if reading that of <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.16. we note what is the Queſtion, and what is the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution. The Queſtion is, Whether it were indifferent for men and women to be covered or not covered in the Church-aſſemblies as they liſted: St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith No, it is not: but the Men muſt do ſo, and the Women ſo: Now ſaith he, <hi>If any man be contentious q: d:</hi> if he will preſumptuouſly contend againſt all reaſon that the thing is indifferent, and ſo he may in this uſe his own liberty: What then<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> why ſaith he, <hi>We have no ſuch Cuſtome, nor the Churches of God: q: d:</hi> The Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the Church which is eſtabliſht muſt over-rule mens froward fancies, and ſtand for a law to quiet the conſcience of him that is willing to be ſatisfied. So then the Cuſtomes of the Church ordained by the Apoſtles are a Ground of ſatisfaction. Nor are they therfore in themſelves leſs authenticall, becauſe they are not mentioned in the text of Scripture, as preſcribed by the Apoſtles, if yet it may appear that from them they fetch their firſt Originall. It is not the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that giveth things their Authority,<note place="margin">See <hi>Hooker: Eccleſiaſticall Polity, lib.</hi> 1 <hi>ſect.</hi> 14. <hi>pag</hi> 44. <hi>Field</hi> on the Church, <hi>lib.</hi> 4.20.</note> but the worth and credit of Him that delivereth them, tho but by word and lively voice onely. More certainty to us-ward things have by writing, but not more Authority in themſelves, <hi>ex: gr.</hi> That ſaying of our Saviour not mentioned by the Evangeliſts,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:111276:6"/> yet now known to be his by the Allegation of St. <hi>Paul, Act.</hi> 20.35. That Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cy of <hi>Enoch, Jude</hi> 14. Theſe in themſelves were no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> leſs authentick truths be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, than after thoſe allegations, So for Apoſtolicall Cuſtomes: Thoſe mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Scripture have a more unqueſtioned Certainty than Traditions, but not greater Authority. Neither is this to ſett up Tradition (as do the Papiſts) to the prejudice of the Scripture; Becauſe we admit none for Apoſtolicall, which either are contrary to the Scripture, or which may not by good reaſon from ſome text of Scripture be confirmed for Apoſtolicall. You ſee whither all this tendeth, <hi>viz.</hi> To make way for this Aſſumption: That if the Baptizing of Infants may reaſonably be judged one of thoſe Apoſtolicall Traditions, one of theſe Church-Cuſtoms, which were eſtabliſhed in the Churches according to the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſt: Then is ther ſufficient Ground in Scripture to warrant the uſe and practiſe of it. And tho ther be no mention of it in the text of Scripture: yet if it may appear to have been ordained by th'Apoſtles, and uſed by the Churches even from the dayes of the Apoſtles, why ſhould it not be acknowledged to be the commandement of Chriſt, and ſo a Ground for Conſcience to build upon. Well: But (you will ſay) how may it appear to have been a cuſtome of the Churches ordained by the Apoſtles? Here it may be worth our Obſervation: That the pattern and preſident from whence moſt (if not all) of them was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aken, was the cuſtome of Iſrael in the Old Teſtament: It is the obſervation of <hi>Jerome.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ut ſciamus traditiones Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolicas ſumptas ex veteri Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>amento; Quod A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ron &amp; fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> ejus at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>, Levit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e in Templo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>crunt, hoc ſibi Epiſcopi Presbyteri, at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Diaconi ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ant in Ecclia — Hieron— Epla. <hi>85.</hi> ad Evagrium.</note> And this may be one ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all reaſon, why the Providence of God did not take ſo much care for the writing of every Cuſtome and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for the Government of the Church-Aſſemblies in the New Teſtament; Becauſe as ther was not ſo much danger of Corruption in them as in points of Doctrine: So the Preſident from whence they were take being at hand, if any aberration did creep in, it might eaſily be amended by reducing it to the pattern. Yea, and who can tell, whether the wiſdom of God did not hereby provide to uphold the credit of the Church of Iſrael, and the Authority of the writings of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets againſt the frowardnes of ſome who were but too apt and ready to diſ-eſteem them. That the Inſtitutions of God by <hi>Moſes</hi> for the Church of Iſrael were the Pattern for the Apoſtolicall Traditions which were appointed for the Diſcipline and Order to be obſerved in the Chriſtian Congregations; it will appear more evidently if we conſider, that the ſubject matter of theſe Orders are, Times, Places, Perſons, and the like. In all which the Apoſtles by the Commandement of Chriſt ſetled ſuch Rules as were conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to what had been formerly in the Church of Iſrael. That we might know, that <hi>no better Orders for the Church can be deviſed, than ſuch as in Conformity to the Church of the Old Teſtament may juſtly, and without wrong to the time of Truth
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111276:6"/> and Grace be framed, and as it were thence tranſlated.</hi> Was it not for this cauſe, that divers particulars which ſhould be in the Chriſtian Churches are propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally deſcribed in phraſes taken from the Church of Iſrael? See theſe texts: <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſai.</hi> 66.21. <hi>&amp;</hi> 23. <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.16. I ſaid, <hi>Without wrong to the time of Truth and Grace,</hi> Becauſe, as ſome judiciall lawes were peculiar to that Nation; and to that Age of the World, and ſo may not be now taken into the Statutes of the Common-wealth: So ſome Eccleſiaſticall Rites were peculiar to that Age of the Church, and may not now be taken into the Canons of the Chriſtian Church: tho others may, which are more morall, and ſo more perpetuall. <hi>Ex. gr.</hi> In the Old Teſtament ther was <hi>one day in ſeven</hi> ſet a part to be a <hi>Day of Holy Reſt; i. e.</hi> a time for the Aſſemblies and Holy Convocations meeting together for the works of Piety and Devotion. In imitation where-of th'Apoſtles by the Direction of our Bleſſed Saviour conſecrated the firſt day of the week to the ſame ends and uſes, and gave it that honourable name which ſtill it beareth <hi>The Lords Day.</hi> Then for <hi>Places</hi> Iſrael had their Synagogues beſide the Temple: And who knoweth not that even in th'Apoſtles times ther were places ſett apart for the Aſſemblies to meet in, and even then began to be called <hi>Churches.</hi> So for <hi>Perſons</hi> Iſrael had thoſe who were ſett apart to the ſervice of the Altar and the Temple: Accordingly the Apoſtles ordained in ſeverall Churches certain Elders, men ſett apart and ſeparated to the work and office of the Miniſtry, who by that ſolemn Rite and Ceremony of their Ordination might be known and acknowledged to receiv from God a ſpeciall deſignation to that function, from which they might not return to ſecular employments and the cares of the world. The maintenance of them, doth St. <hi>Paul</hi> affirm to be ordained of the Lord in conformity to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of the Old Teſtament, <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.13.14. And whether the ſubordination of Some in the Miniſtery to other in the ſame Order were not likewiſe an Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall Inſtitution appointed by Chriſt, and this alſo fetcht from the pattern of <hi>Moſes,</hi> I diſpute not. But this I make no queſtion will be acknowledged by all: That the Cenſures of the Church: That the Directions given to the Church how to proceed in the execution of thoſe Cenſures; That theſe, I ſay were recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from Iſrael: and that not only by the Apoſtles appointing them, <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. but alſo by our Saviour himſelf, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.15. That the Liberty which women have to come to the Table of the Lord muſt be acknowledged a Tradition of the Apoſtles taken from the Pattern of the Paſsover. Nay yet more, The Cuſtome of the Apoſtles to baptiſe the whol houſholds of them that beleeved, and that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly upon the Converſion of the Maſter of the family, and his ſubſcription to the Faith of Chriſt; whence they ſhould have it, except from that like pattern and Preſident in the Old Teſtament, <hi>viz. Abraham</hi> circumciſing all the Males in his houſe, that very day in which the Lord made a Covenant with him, and the practiſe of Iſrael who did the like by all the male-children and infants which
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:111276:7"/> they bought with their money: Whence I ſay that Cuſtome ſhould come, except from this preſident, I ſee not. That they did ſo is evident by the ſtory of their Acts, and being done by them we doubt not of the lawfulnes: No Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation had they for it that is recorded: This Ground of Conformity to the Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of the Old Teſtament we find in others, and therfore conclude this alſo: Now them; The iſſue of all returns to this text. Why this Rule ſhould hold in ſo many particulars, and only fail in this point of Baptiſing Infants, I leav for them to give a reaſon, who know what difference ther is betwixt reaſon and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdity. Eſpecially ſince it is plain enough by the Teſtimony of the Ancients who lived in the next Ages after the Apoſtles, That this alſo was a Cuſtome eſtabliſht by the Apoſtles.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>In</hi> Pam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lius <hi>notes on</hi> Cyprian, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pla. <hi>59. you may find the names of the Ancients who referr it to an Apoſtolicall Tradition. So alſo doth</hi> Augusti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, lib. <hi>4.</hi> De Baptiſmo c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ntra Donatiſt. cap. <hi>23. And in his</hi> Epl. <hi>28.</hi> Ad Hyeronimum, <hi>ſpeaking of the 59 epiſtle of</hi> Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, <hi>the Title wher-of is</hi> Ad Fidum de Infantibus Baptiſandis, <hi>he ſaith,</hi> Beatus Cyprianus non aliquod dec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum condens novum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ed Eccleſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e <hi>fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem firmiſſimam</hi> ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ans ad corri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendum cos, qui putabant ante octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>m nitivitatis non eſſe parvu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum baptiſandum, mox natum rite baptiſari cum ſuis quibusſdam coepiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sopis cenſuit.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Breviat of all this diſcourſ is this: Every Commandement of Chriſt is to be obſerved, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. Infants-Baptiſm is the Commandement of Chriſt; Every Apoſtolicall Inſtitution is the Commandement of Chriſt: Infants Baptiſm is an Apoſtolicall Inſtitution (therfore.) The Major is proved, <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.25. and 14.37. and muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged except we would ſuſpect them of falſ and faithleſs dealing: The Minor is acknowledged by the Ancients; And ther is great reaſon for it, becauſe it doth (as do the reſt of the Rules for Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Diſcipline delivered to the Church) carry in its face and fore-head the ſtamp of Chriſts Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, <hi>viz.</hi> Conformity to the Pattern of the Church of Iſrael.</p>
                  <p>So then; To them who think they may triumph in that Argument produced againſt Infants Baptiſm: That, it being preſuppoſed that the Teſtament of Chriſt is ſo perfect, and he ſo faithfull, that nothing ought to be practiſed of Chriſtians, which is not therein warranted either by Precept, or Pattern: And it being aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that ther is neither Precept nor Pattern for this Cuſtome; Therfore it may not be practiſed, To them I ſay we ſee what Anſwer may be returned.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. To the Major, Flouriſhed with that text of <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.2.6. as <hi>Moſes:</hi> So Chriſt was faithfull: Nay more, <hi>Moſes</hi> only as a ſervant, but Chriſt as a Sonn; And (therfore) his Teſtament as perfect, nay more perfect than that of <hi>Moſes.</hi> True indeed; But know we not, that the faithfulneſs of a man in his office is to be mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured according to the intent and ſcope of his Office impoſed? In which if he fail and faulter, then is he unfaithfull; if not, then is he not unfaithfull tho he look not to other things, <hi>ex. gr.</hi> The Miniſter may be faithfull, tho he meddle not with the Sword of Juſtice: The Magiſtrate, tho he fight not with the ſword of the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:111276:7"/> Spirit. So then, what was the office of <hi>Moſes?</hi> and what of Chriſt? The Office of <hi>Moſes</hi> was to ſettle the Common-wealth, and the Nationall Church of Iſrael: The Office of Chriſt was to make Reconciliation betwixt God and man, to work out the Redemption of Mankind. It was fitt that <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhould ſett down parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular laws for the Common-wealth, and Ordinances for the Church: Neither of theſe did pertain to the Office of Chriſt; yet by his Apoſtles and their ſucceſſors in ſeverall Ages doth he provide whatſoever is neceſſary for the welfare and good order of the Church of the New Teſtament: But in his own perſon, and by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf he eſtabliſhed the Covenant of Grace, ordained the Seals ther-of, ſett up a Miniſtery, gave to them the word of life and ſalvation, and pointed to them a pattern for good Order and Government, and ſo was faithfull in his houſe as a Sonn, and worthy of more honour than <hi>Moſes.</hi> This for the Major.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. To the Minor: We grant, That neither Precept nor Pattern formall and explicite is to be found in the books of the New Teſtament for Infants baptiſing, <hi>i. e.</hi> There is no Precept that ſaith, Go and baptiſe Infants; no more is ther any Precept to baptiſe Women; nor to obſerv the Lords day as a Chriſtian Sabbath: Ther is no text that ſaith, The Children and Infants of this or that man were baptiſed; Nor is ther any text that ſaith, Such a woman was admitted to the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Lord. But we ſay, that both Precept and Pattern virtuall and implicit may be found to warrant it, The which if found is not to be neglected.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Precept Virtuall and implicit.</head>
                  <p>Here we pitch upon the continuation of the Cuſtome in Iſrael to preſent their Infants to the Sacrament of initiation, and we frame the Argument thus. What was inſtituted in the Old Teſtament, and not repealed in the New, nor is any way incompatible with the ſtate of the Church in the New Teſtament, that is underſtood to be continued, and commended to the practiſe of the Chriſtian Church: But that Infants ſhould be initiated and admitted into the Covenant of Grace by a Sacrament, was commanded in the Old Teſtament, neither is it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed in the New, nor incompatible with the ſtate of the New Teſtament (ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.) That it is not repealed is thence confirmed, Becauſe in the Subſtitution of that new Sacrament of Initiation, ther is no particular exception taken againſt Infants, (as before was noted in the firſt Argument. That it is not incompati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with the ſtate of the Church in the New Teſtament is thus further confirmed. 1. The Infants of Chriſtians are as capable of preſent incorporation into Chriſt, and of admiſſion into the Covenant of Grace, as were the infants of the Jews: And if ſo, who ſhall barr them (whom God hath not barred) from the Seal of the Covenant. 2. The Infants of Chriſtians have as much need of the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and Participation in the Covenant of Grace as had the Infants of the Jews: And their Parents as much need of a Ground of comfort, as touching the Remedy
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:111276:8"/> of that which maketh them ſtand in need of the Covenant of Grace and the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits therof as the Parents of Jewiſh Infants. If ſo? who ſhall think that God hath not provided for them ſo well as for the other. If he hath not, how hath Grace abounded in the New Teſtament, when in this particular it is much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreined both to Beleevers, and to their Infants: But if he hath, who ſhall forbid them that, which God hath provided for them?</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That the Infants of Chriſtians are as capable: is proved by that of <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. <hi>They are holy:</hi> And what is that? Ther be who gloſs upon the text and ſay, That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hildren are Holy indeed, but how? As the wife not otherwiſe, <hi>viz.</hi> As ſhe is ſanctified to the uſe of her Husband, ſo the children to the uſe of their Parents: But they falſifie the text: For the text ſaith not of the wife, She is ſanctified <hi>to</hi> her husband, but <hi>by</hi> her Husband, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Nor of the children it is ſaid as of the wife. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>is ſanctified,</hi> but they are <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Holy,</hi> which is more full, and more emphaticall. Others ſhift it of with this: That the children are ſaid to be Holy, becauſe, Notwithſtanding the difference of Religion in the Parents, yet the children are <hi>legitimate.</hi> This is further of than the former; Nor can it ſtand, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept this be preſuppoſed, That all the children of Heathens are illegitimate: No more than the former can ſtand without this being preſuppoſed; That neither wife, nor children of Pagans are ſanctified to their uſe. Wherfore, ther is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing left, but that they are ſaid to be <hi>Holy,</hi> by the Holines of the Covenant, and ſanctified with a federall ſanctification: The which is ſo much the more mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, becauſe it appeareth by the context, That the pretence of them, who did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudiate their wives for their infidelity, was a fear, leſt the infidelity of the wife ſhould deprive the Husband of his intereſt in the Covenant of Grace which hee had imbraced: and that his conjunction with her ſhould rend him of (as did the Sinn of Fornication, <hi>cap.</hi> 6.15.) from Communion with Chriſt. St. <hi>Paul</hi> denyeth this, and ſheweth that rather the Faith of the Beleevers ſhould ſo farr preponderate and prevail as to draw the other parties alſo after a ſort within the Covenant, So that the unbeleeving wife is ſanctified and accounted as one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terreſſed in the Covenant by the Husband: His reaſon is, becauſe otherwiſe the children of ſuch ſhould be accounted <hi>Vnclean,</hi> or altogether barred from the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, wher-as now they are Holy, <hi>i. e.</hi> Heirs of the Covenant, and admitted to the Seals ther-of. <hi>Admitted,</hi> I ſay, For this is worthy our obſervation: That ſuppoſe any of the Corinths would have been ſo wilfull to doubt of this Medium, and deny th'Argument of St. <hi>Paul:</hi> what is ther to convince the Gainſayer, but only the practiſe of Iſrael continued in the Chriſtian Churches, <hi>viz.</hi> That the children of one beleeving Parent are admitted to the Seals of the Covenant. This muſt of Neceſſity be preſuppoſed, elſe doth the Argument fall to the ground and overthrow it ſelf. To ſay, That it reſteth upon the Authority of th'Apoſtles affirmation, is not ſufficient: in as much as he doth not poſitively ſet it down as a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:111276:8"/> thing to be learned, (as he had done the former point, The wife is ſanctified) but brings it in as a Reaſon to confirm that former point: And we know, that the Reaſon of a Poſition is alway preſuppoſed, as a thing already yeelded and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That the Infants of Chriſtians have as much need of partaking in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace, as had the Jewiſh Infants, is thence confirmed: Becauſe, <hi>That which is born of the Fleſh, is fleſh.</hi> Naturall corruption is common to all. Why was Circumciſion ordained, but that ther-by the Uncircumciſion of the Heart might be taken away: that the Corruption of Nature might bee cured, and the Guilt of that firſt ſinn cut off from the Iſrael of God: That <hi>Abraham</hi> by Faith apprehending the promiſe of God might ther-in have a Ground of comfort to himſelf in reſpect of his Sonn, <hi>viz.</hi> That tho he had begotten him in his own like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and had been a mean to convey unto him the Guilt and Filth of Originall ſinn: yet now by the mercy of God, he was provided of a Remedy for that Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lady of his child, and uſing that Sacrament in Faith he might comfortably aſſure himſelf that the Remedy ſhould prevail againſt the Malady: And is not this Ground of comfort needfull alſo for Chriſtians? Surely they are deceived, who either deny the propagation of originall ſinn to Infants; or dream of any Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall Demolition of it by the Death of Chriſt without the particular Application of his Blood by the Sacrament of the Goſpell. If there be no ſuch Malady, no ſuch Guilt in our Infants, how cometh it to paſs that they dy? Is ther any place for Death in Mankind, wher ther is no ſinn at all? If the Beaſts decay and dy by reaſon of their naturall mortality, yet we know that ſinn it was which brought Death upon <hi>Adam</hi> and his Poſterity. Where ther is no ſinn inherent, Death can claim no intereſt in that party: Wher Death ſeizeth upon man, we muſt not deny ſinn, ſome ſin ther muſt be: Actuall, ther is none in theſe Infants. Not yet have they ſinned after the <hi>Similitude of Adams tranſgreſſion, viz.</hi> by li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtening to the Tentation of Satan; and therfore it is Originall Guilt and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which is in them: If the Diſeaſe be in their Nature; Is ther not need of a Remedy? Had the Infants of the Jews a Remedy, and is ther none provided for the Infants of Chriſtians? Is ther a Remedy provided for them, and a ground of comfort for their Parents, and ſhall it be denyed, and they debarred?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Objection.</hi> The force of this Argument, ſome think to elude by denying Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion to be a Seal of the Covenant of Grace, and conſequently no Remedy againſt that originall Malady wher-of we ſpeak: We oppoſe that honourable Elogie of it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4 11. The Apoſtle termeth it, <hi>A Seal of the Righteouſnes of Faith:</hi> They anſwer, it was a ſeal of <hi>Abrahams</hi> Faith, not in the Promiſe of the Meſſiah, and the Covenant of Grace, but in the promiſe of a Neumerous Off-ſpring, <hi>That he ſhould be the Father of many Nations.</hi> This was (ſay they) that part of Gods Covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> which was ſealed by Circumciſion:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:111276:9"/> A fleſhly Covenant had a fleſhly Seal. But in this Anſwer we find a twofold ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance bewrayed. 1. The miſ-interpretation of the Phraſe: <hi>The Righteouſnes of Faith:</hi> A phraſe peculiar to St. <hi>Paul</hi> by which is intimated not the <hi>Act</hi> of Faith, but the <hi>Benefit</hi> ther-of. The phraſe is equivalent to, and to be expounded by that of <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.30. &amp; 10.6. <hi>The Righteouſnes which is by faith,</hi> and that alſo, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 21. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10.3. <hi>The Righteouſnes of God</hi> Both which are joined in one, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.22. <hi>The Righteouſnes of God which is by Faith:</hi> and therby is ſignified the Benefit of imputed Righteouſnes which God beſtoweth on Beleevers for their Juſtification: This benefit God having beſtowed upon <hi>Abraham,</hi> did ſeal it up to Him after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward by Circumciſion, which is therfore called, Not the Seal of his Faith, but the Seal of the Righteouſnes, <hi>i. e.</hi> of Juſtification which cometh by Faith and not by Works. 2. Another point of ignorance, is in diſ-joyning thoſe things which ought not to be diſ-joined, <hi>viz.</hi> the Covenant of Grace, and the Promiſe of a Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous off-ſprings. Is it not evident that in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. ther is ſpeciall mention of the Covenant of Grace, <hi>viz. I will be the God of thee, and thy ſeed after thee</hi>— and then followeth, <hi>Thou ſhalt therfore keep my Covenant, thou and thy ſeed— This is my Covenant- Every man-child among you ſhall be circumciſed.</hi> Why ſhould Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion be reſtreyned to the Promiſe of a Numerous of-ſpring, when the text doth not reſtrein it? If any reply, That in <hi>Gen.</hi> 15. wher the Righteouſnes of Faith is mentioned, to which the Apoſtle alludeth, ther is only mention made of a Numerous of-ſpring promiſed. Be it ſo: But that of <hi>Calvin</hi> is ſound, who ſaith, That whatſoever promiſes God did give to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Jn dubium est axioma apud Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anos quaſcun<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> promiſſiones Abrahae dedit Deus pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mae illius fuiſſe appen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices— Ergo cum audiret Abraham. Erit ſem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n tuum ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ut arena m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>is— in hoc verbo non ſubſtitit, ſed ipſum, potius includebat in gratia Adoptio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis tanquam partem in toto, <hi>Calv. in C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>l. 3 6.</hi>
                     </note> they were Appendices of that firſt promiſe made to Him: and ſo this of a numerous of— ſpring, was by Faith received as a fruit of that firſt Grace he beſtowed on Him <hi>viz.</hi> His Adopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; Nay more, That Promiſe of a Numerous of-ſpring, that he ſhould be the Father of many Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; Was it fulfilled in the children of the fleſh only, or in the children of the Promiſe alſo? And how came he to be the Father of thoſe children, but by Faith in the Covenant of Grace?</p>
                  <p>Conclude (therefore) That Circumciſion was a Seal of the Covenant of Grace; A Remedy of that Diſ-eaſe which is derived from Father to Sonn by Propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Which being in the Poſterity of Beleeving Chriſtians no leſs than in the Poſterity of Beleeving Jewes: It followeth that theſe have as much need as the other: And being <hi>Holy</hi> by virtue of their Parents intereſt in the Covenant, are as capable of this Benefit as the other were. Conſequently that the implantation of Infants into that Myſticall Body of Chriſt by a Sacrament is not incompatible with the ſtate of the Church in the New Teſtament. And if not ſo: Since it is
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:111276:9"/> not repealed by Chriſt and his Apoſtles: we conclude, That ther is a Precept virtuall and implicit: And tho it be not ſaid in direct terms, Go and baptiſe Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers and their Children, yet in that it is ſaid, Circumciſe them, their Baptiſm is included: ſo much the more: Becauſe it will appear that ther is alſo for the Baptiſing of Infants.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Pattern virtuall and Implicit.</head>
                  <p>This is in the Baptiſing of whole Families upon the converſion of the Maſters ther-of, The whole Houſholds of <hi>Lydia, Cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſpus, Cornelius,</hi> and others were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed: To ſay, that in them ther might be no children, becauſe none are mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, is to ſpeak againſt all ſenſe and reaſon. As well may it be ſaid ther were no ſervants, and ſo make up a Family of I know not how few. What ſay we to thoſe <hi>three thouſand ſouls</hi> mentioned, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. which were added to the Church in one day: Is it probable that they were all preſent at the Sermon, and converted to the Faith by that Sermon, it being in a private Houſe? Is it not more proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that the Men being preſent and converted, they brought alſo their Families to be baptiſed, which they might well do, becauſe they heard St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſay: <hi>The Promiſe is made to you and to your children:</hi> So that the totall ſumme of men, women and children might be 3000. ſouls: Some ſuch thing doubtleſs is inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated in that phraſe, 3000. ſouls: anſwerable to that in the ſtory of <hi>Gen.</hi> 46. <hi>ver.</hi> 27. <hi>Act.</hi> 7.14. <hi>All that came down into Egipt with Jacob were</hi> 70 <hi>ſouls.</hi> Souls, <hi>i. e.</hi> perſons, men, women, and children. And here doubtleſs the courſe and practice of the Converts was anſwerable to that in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. No ſooner is the Covenant made with <hi>Abraham,</hi> but he circumciſeth all the Males in his houſe both young and old: So doubtleſs, No ſooner is the Covenant of Grace ratified betwixt Chriſt and the Beleeving Parents by Baptiſm, but the Houſhold is alſo accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Holy</hi> and ſo baptiſed. Doubtleſs, what St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid to them in <hi>Act.</hi> 2. <hi>The Promiſe is made to you and to your children;</hi> The ſame did St. <hi>Paul</hi> preach to the Gentiles when they were converted, that they might know the large bounty of God to them and theirs in the Covenant of Grace: And how ſhould they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm this to them but by baptiſing their children? Take away this, and you leav open a wide gapp to an Objection which is not eaſily anſwered: For they might object: What tell you us of the Grace of God in Chriſt, of the ſuper-abundance of that Grace: Do we not ſee the contrary? This is nothing anſwerable to that of <hi>Abraham</hi> and Iſrael? They by their Faith received a Benefit for their children, yea their ſervants. Not ſo here: We our ſelves per-aduenture may be the better for our Faith: But our children remain ſtill as they were ſtrangers to the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. Will you imagine the Apoſtle to reply: Nay, but the Promiſe is to you and your children. So that when they come to beleev they alſo may be admitted; How juſtly might the Objector rejoin: what great priviledge is this? So may the very Heathen, all that are afarr of when they beleev; If this be all that we
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:111276:10"/> gain; Our children, notwithſtanding our Faith are in no better condition than the Heathen themſelves, Nothing ſo good as the children of the Jews: And ſo the great boaſt of ſuper-abundant Grace falls to the ground. Thus we ſee good Reaſon to acknowledge this Cuſtome of baptiſing Infants to be warranted both by Precept and Pattern, tho not formall and explicite; yet virtuall and implicit; And that with ſo great light and evidence from Scripture, that greater in that kind cannot be expected.</p>
                  <p>Before I proceed to an other Argument: Let me improve this further,</p>
                  <p>That Cuſtome and Practiſe of the Church may well be preſumed to be Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall, which is ſo conſonant to the text of Scripture, that it doth readily illuſtrate the text: and openeth a door of light to underſtand the ſame: Such is the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of Infants Baptiſed therfore. That which being granted giveth light: and which being denyed doth leave the text under ſuch a cloud of obſcurity, that it is not eaſily underſtood how it may paſs for Truth: This muſt be granted to open a door of light to underſtand the text of Scripture. Now then, ſuppoſe this Act of the Apoſtles baptiſing Infants: we eaſily ſee how 3000. ſouls may be added to the Church in one day, notwithſtanding the Sermon were in a privat houſe: We ſee how St. <hi>Peter</hi> might confirm their Beleef in this, <hi>The Promiſe is made to you, and to your children:</hi> even the Promiſe of ſuper-abundant Grace: We ſee how St. <hi>Paul</hi> might urge this, <hi>your children are Holy:</hi> But take away the ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of this Cuſtome, and none of theſe texts are ſo eaſie to be underſtood. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently: it is more than probable, that even this Cuſtome of Baptiſing Infants was inſtituted and ordained in the Churches by th'Apoſtles: and that according to the commandement of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Add unto all that hath been ſayd that of St. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Sicut nunc in eccleſià manet Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutio ſalvatoris dicentis, Niſi quis renatus ſucrit — Ita ſacratiſſimè in lege ſuerat praecautum, ut natus puer niſi die circumcideretur octavo, exterminaretur anima ejas de populo ſuo— Ambroſ. Epiſt. 33. Ad Deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triadem. p. 132.</note> who ſetts theſe two as paralell: the law of God, touching Circumciſion, <hi>The ſoul who is not circumciſed, ſhall be cut off from his people:</hi> and the Sanction of our Saviour: <hi>Except a man bee born again of water, and of the Spirit, he cannot enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the kingdome of God.</hi> That this text is to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of Baptiſm, as a mean and cauſe of Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, Not ſo principall as the Spirit: yet ſo inſtrumentall to the Spirit, that wher it may be had, wee have no ground of Faith to beleev that the Spirit will work without it: This is I ſay the conſtant and conſentient judgement of all the Ancients, and moſt of our modern Divines; Some few only excepted, who to avoid the Popiſh Tenet, touching the abſolute neceſſity of B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ptiſm, did fly to a Metaphor. And it may be confirmed for Truth, out of the Text it ſelf: if we note well, <hi>To whom,</hi> and <hi>upon what</hi> occaſion the words were ſpoken: <hi>viz.</hi> To <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> upon occaſion of his timerouſnes: A Diſciple of Chriſt, he was
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:111276:10"/> willing to be, but loth to proſeſs it openly by being baptiſed. To him is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination directed: and therfore the words muſt be underſtood of Baptiſm: Now then conſider well, whether ther be any ground ſufficient to keep of Infants from this Ordinance? Any ground (I ſay) which may ſecure the conſcience of not having ſinned againſt the ſouls of our Infants, if by our default they dy without this ſeal of the Covenant, and ſo looſ the Benefit ther-of? Have not Infants need of Chriſt, and the Application of his Blood for the waſhing their ſouls from ſinn? Is ther any Hope of Salvation without Chriſt? Is ther any other way re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, by which any may have part in Chriſt, but by his Ordinances? Is ther any other Ordinance by which Infants may be made partakers of Chriſt and the Covenant of Grace except Baptiſm? Is ther any text of Scripture that hath pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptorily barred their Admittance? Or is ther any thing required of them that muſt be baptiſed, the want wher-of may be a barr to Infants? Thou doubteſt, becauſe ther is no text that mentioneth either Precept or Pattern, and with-out a text, thou dareſt not venture: 'Tis well: But when ther is ſuch a fearfull ſentence, that runns in ſuch generall terms as doth comprehend Infants alſo: and the Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Omiſſion is ſo great: Why art thou not more cautelous on the ſafer ſide? Why doſt thou not as well call for a direct text to barr them? or a direct Reaſon from Scripture, which may be equivalent? Is ther any text that ſaith, None may be baptiſed, that do not Beleev? or that ſaith Infants for want of Actuall faith may not be baptiſed? Doeſt thou not ſee Infants Circumciſed yea by command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Doeſt thou not hear the text that ſaith, <hi>Children are Holy?</hi> And are ther ſo many Probabilities that by th'Apoſtles themſelves Infants were baptiſed? And wilt thou rather hazard the ſoul of thy child, than lay hold upon the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant for thy ſeed, nay for thy ſelf? and that only upon a fear, and a doubt of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfulnes; yea ſuch a doubt that hath no ſurer ground either in Scripture or Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to countenance it, than the contrary reſolution?</p>
                  <p>Here is then the Caſe: if theſe Grounds formerly mentioned prove good, as ther is great probability: Then thou preſenting thine Infant to Baptiſm build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon theſe grounds, thou haſt ſaved thy ſelf and thine Infant: but forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and keeping him of, thou ſinneſt againſt thine own ſoul and his alſo: Again, if thoſe grounds ſhould not prove good: yet haſt thou not wronged thine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant, nor thine own ſelf: Becauſe, upon ſuch probabilities as are next door to an Evident Demonſtration, thou haſt done that which is intended for the Glory of God, and the Good of the Infant. Thou haſt not tranſgreſſed againſt any Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, no nor any light of Reaſon which might juſtly with-hold thee from ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Good of thine Infant at the Hands of Chriſt in this Ordinance.</p>
                  <p>I conclude therfore, That ther is ſufficient Ground in Scripture to warrant the Conſcience of a Chriſtian to bring his Infants to this Sacrament of Baptiſm,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:111276:11"/> with a confident expectation to receiv Benefit by the ſame. Nay more: Ther is Ground enough to warrant the Accuſation of Him that upon ſuch uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Reaſons ſhall forbear to preſent his Infant to this Sacrament of Initia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Accuſation I ſay of Him, as one that ſinneth againſt the Ordinance of God, and treſpaſſeth againſt the Soul of his Infant, yea of Himſelf.</p>
               </div>
               <trailer>So much for the firſt Queſtion.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="answer">
               <head>
                  <hi>THE SECOND QVESTION. Queſt.</hi> Whether it be not ſinfull, for a Chriſtian to receiv the Sacrament in a mixt Aſsembly.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Mixt Aſſembly is that, wherein good and badd are mingled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and make up one Congregation; when the <hi>precious</hi> are not ſevered from the <hi>vile,</hi> nor any difference put between the <hi>Holy</hi> and <hi>Prophane.</hi> Now theſe good and badd, theſe precious and vile, are not to be reckoned in reſpect of their ſpirituall eſtate toward God, i. e. as they are Elect or Reprobate, Sincere or Hypocriticall: but in reſpect of their Eccleſiaſticall ſtate in the ey and judgement of Men, as they are in their courſes and converſations, in their Calling and Profeſſion holy or profane. Theſe bad, and vile, are again to be conſidered <hi>A parte ante,</hi> or <hi>A parte poſt,</hi> viz. Either ſuch as yet profeſs not themſelves in Covenant with God, by joining themſelves to the Aſſembly of his ſervants: Or ſuch, who having formerly had a ſtanding in the Church, do afterward run out into exorbitant courſes to the ſcandall of Religion, and ſo deſerv to be ſeparated from the Society of the Saints, and by the Sentence of Excommunication cut of from the Aſſembly. So that the Queſtion is, Whether if either of theſe be found in the Congregation and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of them, that draw neer to the Table of the Lord to partake of thoſe holy Myſteries; either thoſe, who as yet have not been admitted, or thoſe that by the laws of Chriſt ought to be ſhutt out and ſequeſtred, whether their preſence do make it unlawfull in point of conſcience for a Chriſtian to receiv the Sacrament among them, ſo that if he do, he is <hi>eo nomine,</hi> therby deſiled, and become parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of their ſinn.</p>
               <p>Where alſo for the better underſtanding of the Anſwer to this Queſtion, we are to note, what is granted: and what is queſtioned and demanded.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:111276:11"/>
               <p>Things granted are theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Some are not to be admitted to the Table of the Lord.</hi> This is evident enough No uncircumciſed perſon might eat of the Paſſover: Nor any perſon unbaptiſed be admitted to the Lords Supper, how morally righteous ſoever he bee. The Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon her-of is, Becauſe, None may be received into the Communion and fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the Church, till he have profeſſed himſelf one of them that deſire to lay hold on the Hope of Eternall life by the Mean and Mediation of Chriſt, in whom alone is founded the Covenant of Grace. Now this Profeſſion is by ſubmitting himſelf to the Sacrament of Baptiſm. Hence it is that our Bleſſed Saviour hath joined theſe two together, <hi>He that beleeveth and is baptiſed.</hi> As none unbapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: So not all that are baptiſed. Children ſo ſoon as they be able to learn muſt be taught, and by teaching be fitted <hi>to diſcern the Lords Body</hi> before they be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to it: Of old, Iſrael muſt inſtruct their children in the Rites of the Paſſover:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod</hi> 12 26 <hi>&amp;</hi> 13.14.</note> In imitation wher-of Chriſtians receiv a charge touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their children, to bring them up in the knowledge and practiſe of their holy Profeſſion. Yea, and by an Apoſtolicall Ordinance (as it is probable from that of <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2.) The Paſtours of the Church in all ages according to the truſt committed to them, have taken an account of what the Parents have done in this Education of their children, examining them in the Articles of their Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leef, and the points of the Catechiſm, And ther-upon have approved thoſe whom they found Proficients, and by their Benediction have confirmed and comforted them in theſe their happy Beginnings. This Order of ſolemn Confirmation is acknowledged by the Godly learned to be of merveilous good uſe in the Church. And reaſon giveth it ſo to be: That ſo, when children are come to a perfect Age, and in ſome meaſure able to underſtand the matters of Religion, and to give an account of their Faith, they may then make an open profeſſion of their Beleef, and an open promiſe of their Obedience to the laws of God: and ſo ther-upon in a ſolemn maner be admitted to the holy Communion. And till they be thus confirmed, I ſhould yeeld it altogether unfitting (at leaſt for Orders ſake) that any be admitted to the Table of the Lord.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Some are to be ſhutt out and ſequeſtred.</hi> No doubt of this: <hi>Adam</hi> was thruſt out of Paradiſe, that he might not taſt of the Tree of life, and feed himſelf with a vain hope of immortality. The Leprous were to be ſhut out of the Camp: They that were unclean by a dead body, <hi>Num.</hi> 9.6. could not keep the Paſſover on the day. The Refractary and Obſtinate is to be accounted as an Heathen. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17. The inceſtuous perſon muſt be delivered to Satan, and Scandalous Chriſtians excluded from <hi>civill,</hi> much more from <hi>ſacred</hi> Communion. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. Such order muſt be taken alſo with in-ordinate walkers, 2 <hi>Theſs.</hi> 3. and with unreformable Heretiks, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.10. If any man love not the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>i. e.</hi> if any walk in a manifeſt Profeſſion of Diſlike and Deteſtation of Chriſt and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:111276:12"/> his Goſpel, He muſt be pronounced Anathema: This is the Diſcipline of the Church: and good is the Reaſon ther-of, 1. <hi>In reſpect of the Perſons Delinquent:</hi> That by the deſtruction of the Fleſh the Spirit may be ſaved: This was an wholſome ſeverity, a Church-puniſhment, inflicted as a means appointed of God to reduce and reclaim thoſe who were not deſperately given up to a repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate ſenſe. 2. <hi>In reſpect of the Congregation,</hi> that others might hear and fear: That others might ſhun familiarity wi h them for fear of infection by them. 3. <hi>In reſpect of them that are without the Church:</hi> That the name of the Lord might not be blaſphemed by them: but that they might ſee and know, that as the Profeſſion, ſo the practiſe of the Church is a conſtant care of holines. Nor will the Church of God indure it, that any of their Society ſhall ſay one thing and do another, talk holines, and live profanely: If any do forget himſelf, and conform to the Men of the World in exorbitant courſes, he ſhall be ſhutt out from among them, and cut off from their Communion: that ſo the whol Aſſembly may even in the ey of the world be found in ſome meaſure conformable to the Holineſs of Chriſt their Head. For theſe Reaſons ſome are to be ſhutt out and ſequeſtred. The firſt and ſecond Reaſons are perpetuall, and preſs the Execution of this point of Diſcipline at all times: The third was more urgent in the times of the firſt Plantation of the Church: And in that reſpect it was (as I conceiv) that the Primitive Churches were ſo ſevere and rigid, even to an over-great meaſure of extremity till experience taught them the Neceſſity of ſome more mildnes and moderation. But yet alway ther is uſe of this point of Diſcipline, to ſeperate and cut off ſcandalous perſons: that ſo the members of the Church may be ſecured from infection, and the whol Body from ſcandal and imputation.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>The Neglect of the Church-Officers in doing their duty, is a ſinn that may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the whol Congregation to the judgements of God:</hi> Their office it is to watch over the Holy things of God, that they be not laid open to contempt, either by admitting them that are not fitted, or by not ſequeſtring them that ought to be ſequeſtred: And their Negligence is a provoking ſinn: was it not upon this ground, that the Congregation doth ſmart in the caſe of <hi>Achan?</hi> The Elders and officers were not ſo carefull as they ſhould have been. To which if ther be added alſo the Neglect of inferiour perſons in doing what they ought (it is their part to be eys and ears to the Governours, informing them of what is amiſs: yea, and in a dutifull way to admoniſh them of their duty, and intreat their diligent circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection, which if they do not, much more if they do approve of their ſlackneſs, and like of them the better, becauſe they are not ſo officious.) What wonder if this Neglect of the Governour prove the deſtruction of the whol Congregation: underſtand this in reſpect of temporall judgements: God to ſhew his juſt indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation againſt ſin: and to teach all and every one to have a care of others, both to greev for them, and to admoniſh them, doth for the ſin of ſome one, eſpecially
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:111276:12"/> if an eminent perſon, cauſe the whol to ſmart under the Rodd of ſome common Calamity. This alſo is not denyed.</p>
               <p>Theſe things being premiſed, as things granted, and not at all queſtioned.</p>
               <p>The Scruple doth ly in this one particular. Whether the ſinn of the unworthy and wicked perſon, intruding himſelf into the company of them that draw neer to the Table of the Lord: and the ſinn of the Church-officers who ſhould (but do not) exclude him, whether this ſinn of theirs defile the Conſcience of Him (a private Chriſtian) who hath no further communion with them, ſave only that he is in their company, and they in his, when he goeth up to the Table of the Lord: He neither approveth of them, nay is greeved for the diſ-order; Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is he defiled?</p>
               <p>To this I anſwer Negatively: It is not (alway) ſinfull for a private Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an to receiv the Sacrament in the company of them that are unworthy Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicants, nay worthy of Excommunication. <hi>Not alway,</hi> I ſay, Becauſe I liſt not to plead the cauſe of them, who for ſome private reſpects do voluntarily chuſe the Society of ſome wicked perſons, when it is in their liberty to make a better choice, But where it is not: As it is not in the choice of Pariſhioners to refuſe their Pariſh Church to which by the juſt law of the Magiſtrate they are bound for Order ſake: Now that in this caſe it is not ſinfull: I prove by theſe Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <div n="1" type="argument">
                  <head>The firſt Argument.</head>
                  <p>VVHat no text of Scripture hath manifeſted to be unlawfull, that is not ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: For in as much as <hi>Sin is the Tranſgreſſion of the law,</hi> what is not unlawfull, that is not ſinfull: And if the text of Scripture doth not manifeſt a thing unlawfull, who ſhall dare to do it. That no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ext of Scripture hath mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted it unlawfull for a private Chriſtian in this caſe to come in the company of the unworthy, it is evidenced by this, That ther is neither any text of Prohibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to forbid it, nor any text of Reprehenſion that hath blamed thoſe that have done it: Conſequent-ly it is not by text of Scripture manifeſted to be unlawfull, and therfore not ſinfull. As we conclude that lawfull, that by text is either com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded or commended. So that, unlawfull, that is either prohibited or reproved.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>1. No text of Scripture hath forbidden it.</head>
                     <p>Not that of <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. No not in that new tranſlation, which ſome put in capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall letters, as if ther were ſome great myſtery in it: NOT TO BE MIXT TOGETHER. Truth it is, ther is a Prohibition directed to the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> and it pertaineth to all the members ther-of: The Prohibition is to them, Not to keep company with ſcandalous Chriſtians, no not to eat with ſuch a one. But it is manifeſt that this Prohibition is not touching <hi>Sacred</hi> but <hi>civill</hi> Society: That company-keeping is in the Citty, not in the Church: That eating is at their own Table, not at the Table of the Lord. Th'Apoſtle had written to them a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:111276:13"/> former Epiſtle, Not to keep company with Fornicators and other ſcandalous perſons: Fain he would that Chriſtians ſhould not only forbear ſuch ſinfull courſes, but even the company of them that were therwith-all defiled: This his Epiſtle and his charge in it, he doth now interpret. ſhewing, That he did not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to forbid them all company or ſociety with thoſe of that ill-name which were not of the Church; This had been to have ſhut them up in a cloiſter, to have baniſhed them out of the world, to have impoſed upon them an impoſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; ſo St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> you muſt ſeek another world to live in, ſeeing the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aſe of Gods people in this world, is as of Roſes among thorns, they cannot but live among the wicked: But, that, if ther were any profeſſed Chriſtians, that yet had not reformed thoſe evill courſes, but ſtill lived in the uſuall practiſe of them, with ſuch a one they muſt have no familiarity, <hi>No not to eat with them.</hi> So then, The eating forbidden is ſuch as is not forbidden in Relation to men of the world: Now with the men of the world they never had any company at the Table of the Lord: Conſequent-ly, the text doth not reſpect that ſacred Communion, nor their joining with the ſcandalous in that ſacred Action. This phraſe <hi>Eat not with him,</hi> is the ſame in effect with that of 2 <hi>Joh.</hi> 10. <hi>Receiv him not into your Houſe</hi> It was altogether unlawfull for the <hi>Corinths</hi> to invite ſuch a ſcandalous Brother to their houſes, or to ſhew him any courteſie; yea, I ſuppoſe the phraſe doth reach further, even to refuſe his invitation, <hi>q. d.</hi> Neither invite him to eat with you, nor accept of any invitation to eat with him; that ſo all ſhew of Familiarity betwixt him and you may be avoided. Add this; It cannot be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of that holy Society which is among Chriſtians at the Lords Table, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>auſe that <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>No not to eat,</hi> intimateth the leaſt familiarity that may be; For ſo is the Argument, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, Not to keep company, no nor to eat: But in that Holy ſociety which Chriſtians have one with another in the Houſe of God, this <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. To eat together is the greateſt: Whence it is that the aggravation of the Puniſhment of obſtinate perſons doth runn in a contrary courſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>; they are firſt ſhut out from the Table of the Lord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and afterward from the Houſes and Tables of Chriſtians. So then, this text of <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. not reſpecting the familiarity and company of them that come to the Lords Table, cannot be alledged to prove it unlawfull, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for a Chriſtian to be found in company, and to go along with the wicked to the Table of the Lord.</p>
                     <p>Nor that of 2 <hi>Theſs.</hi> 3.14. The words are theſe: <hi>If any man obey not our word by this Epiſtle, Note that man, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ave no company with him, that he may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed.</hi> Here it is forbidden to have company with a brother that walketh diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly: So in <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. <hi>viz.</hi> He ſpeaks of them that were idle and buſi-bodyes, <hi>verſ.</hi> 11. The Chriſtians of <hi>Theſſalonica</hi> were moſt of them Artiſans and Labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers; and for thoſe to live idly out of a Calling was a diſ-orderly walking: and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:111276:13"/> thoſe the Apoſtle would have to be puniſhed: The puniſhment is ſet down, <hi>ver.</hi> 6. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>: To withdraw themſelves from him; and <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. To keep no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with him: Now this company cannot be underſtood of the holy Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe it is ſubjoined to the verb <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>Note that man,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Calvin Beza, Bullinger: Marlorat.</note> which by divers Godly and Learned is interpreted the Act of Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication: <hi>q. d.</hi> Excommunicate him, and have no company with Him: Put him out of the Church: yea, out of all Civill familiarity: Neither in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite him to houſe, nor willingly be yee found in his company. Which is yet more manifeſt; if we conſider, that this <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, is to ſet ſuch a note upon Him as may make him aſhamed: Now that could not be by forbearing to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate in his company. In very deed who ſhould forbear? Is not the Precept di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to the whol Church? Should they all forbear the Communion, and leav him alone at it? <hi>Ridiculum.</hi> No, they muſt all perform their duty, each in his place: The Church-officers muſt ſet a note upon him: <hi>i. e.</hi> Denounce him as an unworthy member of the Church, unfit to be admitted, not only to the Table of the Lord, but even unfit to be admitted to any familiarity and ſociety with them: The Church-members muſt do accordingly, <hi>i. e.</hi> forbear all commerce and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with him; they muſt ſhun him as a Peſt and a Plague-ſore. So then, neither of theſe two texts relating properly and directly to the Table of the Lord can be underſtood, as prohibiting private Chriſtians to communicate in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of them that ought not to be admitted. <hi>Sublato ſubjecto quaeſtionis, collun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur &amp; accidentia.</hi> Much leſs thoſe other texts which are by ſome added <hi>ex abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danti</hi> to fill up room rather then to confirm that cauſe, <hi>viz. Act.</hi> 2.40. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.11. <hi>Theſs.</hi> 5.22. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2.5. For why? When St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>Save your ſelves from this untoward generation.</hi> Doth he ſpeak of misbehaviour'd Chriſtians? or rather of misbeleeving Jews? And is it a work of Darkneſs? Is it an <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of evill</hi> to attend on Gods ordinance? If it be not ſo well performed by theſe wicked ones as it ought; yet is it not to be accounted evill. Surely it is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a work of light, and an Appearance of good, how-ſoever to the wicked and unprepared nothing profitable, is ther no difference betwixt what is evill in the Subſtance of the Act, and what is ſo only by Accident, <hi>viz.</hi> through ſome deſert of the Actor. <hi>From ſuch turn away</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle.) What then? Muſt I therfore turn away from the Communion if they come to it? No: but in the courſe of my converſation I muſt have nothing to do with them: Nay more, that text doth not neceſſarily prove that I muſt turn away ſuch from the Holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion; much leſs doth it prove that I muſt turn away my ſelf becauſe of them. None of thoſe texts do ſpeak home to the point, leaſt of all that of,</p>
                     <p>2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. This text doth indeed call for ſeparation: but from whom? Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect this out of the Coherence. In <hi>ver.</hi> 14. <hi>Be not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>un-equally yoked with un-beleevers, Not yoked ſc.</hi> in ſociety and partnerſhip of the ſhop and ſtock: in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:111276:14"/> Cohabitation and company of the Bed and Bord: Thus to be joined in ſociety with Infidels he counteth a yoke, an unequall yoke; and would have them take heed of it. His Argument is taken from the unequall condition of them: To do this is to couple Righteouſnes with Unrighteouſnes, Light with Darkneſs; Chriſt with Belial: the Temple of God with Idols: things that can have no commerce together, nor communion: And then inferreth, <hi>Wherfore come out from among them, and be yee ſeparate (ſaith the Lord) and touch not the unclean thing, &amp;c.</hi> The Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> lived in the midſt of Infidels: No wonder therfore if the Apoſtle call upon them to ſeparate from ſuch, to take heed of communion with them, eſpecially in that which he had taxed under the name of Idolatry, and here under that phraſe, <hi>Touch not the unclean thing; ſc.</hi> their preſence at the Idolatrous feaſts, This in ſpeciall would he have them forbear; Now I pray, what is this to the preſence of the worthy receiver in the company of unworthy Communicants at the Table of the Lord? Is not he blind that ſeeth not a large difference, and that the one doth not draw on the other to be unlawfull? Will it follow, that becauſe the Corinthians who were preſent with Idolaters at their Idol-feaſts, are ſaid to have communion with Idolaters, that therfore he who is in the company of wicked men in their approaching to the Table of the Lord, doth partake with them in their wickednes? If ſo: Then as the Corinths by ſo doing are ſaid to <hi>touch the unclean thing:</hi> So alſo theſe Receivers of whom wee ſpeak, by ſo doing do alſo touch the unclean thing. And ſhall we call the Table of the Lord an unclean thing? Is it alſo an Idol? Ther is a text in <hi>Hagg.</hi> 2. <hi>ver.</hi> 12— 14. which had wont to be alledged to prove that wicked men defile the Ordinances of God. But if ſo, it is but to themſelves not to others: As wholſom meat received into a corrupted ſtomack turns into noxious humours: and the ſame word that is to ſome the ſavour of life, is to others (in whom it is not mixed with faith) the ſavour of Death; to theſe, but not to others in their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: Ther is an errour in theſe mens underſtanding: They conceiv, that meerly to be in company with the wicked, is to communicate with them in their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: They are deceived: To communicate in wickedneſs, is to join fellowſhip in the purſuit of wicked intentions: <hi>ex. gr.</hi> When wicked men take in hand a wicked purpoſe (to honour an Idol, to ſet up profaneſs; to act in the works of darknes, murther, adultery, theevery, perjury, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Then to join ſociety with them wittingly, is to communicate with them in wickednes. <hi>Wittingly,</hi> I ſay: For thoſe 200. that in the ſimplicity of their heart went along with <hi>Abſalom</hi> to <hi>Hebron,</hi> did not communicate with him in his treaſon tho they went in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany. But now, Will any man of wit or reaſon ſay, That theſe wicked men, and theſe ſcandalous Brethren, who come to the Table of the Lord unworthily, that they go about a wicked purpoſe and intention? ſurely, what faultines ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is in them, by which they barr themſelves from the Benefit of the Lords
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:111276:14"/> Table; yet the thing that they go about, in it ſelfe is good, a duty enjoined, yea ſo acknowledged by them, in which reſpect it is that they addreſs themſelves unto it: And therfore they that go with them to this, do communicate with them in Good; becauſe they do willingly join their company in the proſecution of thoſe good intentions. So then none of theſe texts do ſpeak to the point.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Object.</hi> But it will be replyed: That tho the letter of the text doth only look upon civill ſociety prohibiting that as unlawfull: yet by conſequence it will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; That if the one, yea that which is the leſs be unlawfull, then the other, yea much more that that is the greater is unlawfull; <hi>If no Civill, much leſs any ſacred Society.</hi> True: but then, you muſt preſuppoſe the ſame power of Admitting and ſeparating: If I may not admit him to mine houſe, much leſs may I admit him to the Table of the Lord: ſuppoſing me to have the power of Admitting. I grant, that for them that have power to keep him out, the Argument holdeth. The Church-officers of <hi>Corinth</hi> and <hi>Theſſalonica</hi> were bound to make that inference upon the text of St. <hi>Paul;</hi> And if they did not, I acknowledge them to have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. But the caſe is other wiſe in this matter: This doth not prove, that every particular Chriſtian in either of thoſe Churches did ſinn in comming to the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Lord while theſe were not removed, if not they, then neither is it ſinn in any of our Church-members to preſent himſelf at the Holy Table, to partake of thoſe holy Myſteries in the company of them that are unworthy. For why? The Table is the Lords: it is he that maketh the feaſt, that inviteth the gueſts, and bids them welcome: Shall any that is invited and prepared yet abſtain becauſe of anothers unpreparednes? Tell mee I pray you: Did that text of the Apoſtle <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. forbid any Chriſtian to eat at another mans table, ſuppoſing that this other man hath alſo invited a ſcandalous Chriſtian? I trow not. By vertue of that text I may not (as before was ſaid) invite the ſcandalous brother, I may not accept of his invitation. But if a third man invite us both, this text doth not bind me to refuſe my friends curteſie becauſe of ſuch company. If not ſo: much leſs to refuſe the invitation of God calling me to feaſt at his holy Table. Did any of thoſe gueſts in the Parable <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. turn back when they ſaw the Man who had not on his wedding garment, and conſequently in the ſtate of manifeſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthines and unpreparednes? Did they I ſay turn back? or is any of them checked for coming in his company? Which brings on the ſecond part of the firſt Argument, <hi>viz.</hi> That as this caſe is not prohibited, ſo neither is it reprehended.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>2. No text of Scripture hath reprehended it.</head>
                     <p>Not that in <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1.2. Ther indeed he taxeth the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> that they ſuffered the inceſtuous perſon ſtill to remain in Communion with them. He blameth them that they <hi>were puffed up, i. e.</hi> they ſought to hide and excuſe the fault glorying in the excellency of the mans gifts (for it is conceived that he was a Teacher among them, and that for the eminency of his gifts, they were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:111276:15"/> to ſeparate him from the Congregation.) This he chargeth upon them: <hi>and that they had not mourned:</hi> What is meant by this mourning is not eaſily to determine: That is not to be doubted which ſome ſay, <hi>viz.</hi> That ther is good reaſon why we ſhould mourn for the ſin of others (as did thoſe in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 9.4. who are ther-upon marked in the forehead to be preſerved from the common de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction) good reaſon, I ſay, both becauſe hereby there groweth a ſcandall upon the Congregation; as alſo, becauſe the ſinns of others do indanger us (except we mourn for them) in reſpect of temporall things both goods and life, and all: This I ſay is not doubted, yet I rather lean to the opinion of them who under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand this mourning, of the indicting a ſolemn day of Faſting and mourning for the excommunication of that inceſtuous perſon: The cuſtom then was to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the ſentence of Excommunication in a ſolemn maner, with the generall mourning and lamentation of the whol aſſembly invited ther-unto by appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a time for that Action, So much the learned do obſerv out of this text, <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.2. &amp; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.0. And this is that that I conceiv the Apoſtle meaneth in ſaying, <hi>Yee have not mourned, that he might be put away from among you.</hi> And was this the Duty of every particular perſon in the Congregation? The Epiſtle indeed is written to the whol Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> &amp; reſpecteth every particular perſon in the Congregation: But I ſuppoſe that St. <hi>Paul</hi> doth not intend to accuſe every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular member either of being puffed, or of not mourning: much leſs to injoin every man to put on that ſolemn maner of mourning by indiction of the day, and denouncing the ſentence of Excommunication againſt him.</p>
                     <p>To beleev that whatſoever is ſpoken to the whol Congregation may be exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by every particular member ther-of, is in effect to take away diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Orders and officers in the Church and Common-wealth: When God ſaith <hi>Deut.</hi> 13. <hi>That intiſers to Jdolatry muſt be ſtoned to death;</hi> Doth he intend to put every man in Authority to ſee the execution done immediately; Nay, in caſe the Magiſtrate neglect his office, doth this warrantiſe every man to put the law in execution? Doth not this law of God rather intend that execution paſs on legally by the hand of the Officers deputed to hear and determin of ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters? When St. <hi>Paul</hi> writing to the Colloſſians, <hi>Col.</hi> 4.17. putteth in this exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, <hi>And ſay to Archippus, Take heed to the Miniſtry which thou haſt received in the Lord, that thou fulfill it;</hi> Doth he hereby authoriſe every Colloſſian to lay this charge upon the Miniſter? Or is it not rather to be preſented to him by the hands of them that were in place and authority? So neither in <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. He that was not puffed up, was not guilty of communicating in that ſin. And ſuppoſe that the Church-officers had not done their duty in removing the inceſtuous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon (as perhaps they did not remove ſome other ſcandalous brethren from the Church-ſociety) ther is nothing in the text to lead us to beleev that St. <hi>Paul</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended a reproof to them that were <hi>not puffed,</hi> but indeed <hi>mourned</hi> privately in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:111276:15"/> their devotions to ſee ſuch diſorder, a reproof I ſay to them, for that they did not with-draw themſelves from the Communion of the Church in their approaching to the Table of the Lord.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. He reprehendeth them who held Communion with Idolaters in their Idol-feaſts: and in <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. them who profaned the Table of the Lord by their unreverent carriage and behaviour at it: uſing many Arguments to diſwade them from that evill, and to perſwade them to a reformation: yet doth he not ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mention this as a motive, that they did bring ſin upon others, or admoniſh others to forbear communion with them till theſe things were reformed, leaſt ther-by their conſcience ſhould be defiled, and the ordinance of God become un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable to them. Yet this had been a very powerfull Argument of perſuaſion both to the one &amp; to the other, and doubtleſs had ther been truth in it, St. <hi>Paul</hi> would not have forgotten it. The unworthy receiver (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>eateth and drinketh damnation to himſelf:</hi> He ſaith not, to himſelf and others: I grant, it doth not follow from the ſilence of the Apoſtle, that his ſin cannot hurt another beſide himſelf: But this doth follow; That if to him that hath prepared himſelf ther had been any danger at all from the preſence of others who are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, this had been a fit place for St. <hi>Paul</hi> to have mentioned it. Which ſince he hath not, we conclude, that he who hath examined himſelf, hath done enough to ſecure him from the danger of eating and drinking damnation to himſelf, When the Apoſtle doth ſet down the cauſes of that plague that was among the Corinths doth he mention any ſuch thing as their preſence with the wicked in the Duty of Receiving? Or doth the text any wher at all imply it?</p>
                     <p>We find in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.26. a complaint of the Prieſts that they had <hi>violated,</hi> and offered violence to the law: that they had <hi>profaned the Holy things</hi> of God: that they <hi>put no difference between the Holy and Profane, nor ſhewed difference between the clean and unclean.</hi> And in <hi>Jer.</hi> 15.9. the Lord by ſhewing the Prophet what he would have him to doe, intimateth a Reprehenſion of the falſ-prophets who had not done their duty, <hi>viz.</hi> To <hi>ſeparate the pretious from the vile.</hi> But if we look upon the places and weigh them well, we may obſerv that both texts have reference to the Duty of Teachers and Officers in the Church: They muſt indeed put a difference betwixt things holy and profane, they muſt ſeparate the precious from the vile, pronouncing mercy to the one, denouncing judgement to the other: admitting the one to the Holy things, keeping of the other: This muſt they do, and if not, they deſerve a juſt reproof. But what is this to the cauſe in hand? Doth this countenance the courſe of ſuch who condemn thoſe that do not put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the Holy things of Gods becauſe thoſe be admitted which ought not? Is not this rather to make ſad the Heart of the righteous? That of <hi>Eſay</hi> 65.11. <hi>Yee are they that forſake the Lord that prepare a Table for the Troup, and furniſh a drink-offering for the number.</hi> This I ſay hath been alledged to tax the negligence
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:111276:16"/> of them who admit the promiſcuous multitude to the Table of the Lord: As if the Prophet had blamed Iſrael for the like careleſneſs in their Paſſover and Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offering, wheras the text doth blame their Idolatry, not their profaneſs: Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try in ſacrificing to <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Mercury:</hi> to the Hoſt of Heaven. But admit it as a tax of negligence and profaneſs, yet muſt it not fall upon every particular perſon: Apply it to the Church officers and ſpare not: but blame not them, who becauſe the promiſcuous multitude are not turn'd away, do not turn away them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the Table of the Lord. And ſo much for the firſt Argument, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="argument">
                  <head>The ſecond Argument.</head>
                  <p>NO man may neglect, either the Duty that he oweth to God; or the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit which God reacheth forth to Him upon pretence that another man doth not perform his Duty, or is not fitted to receive the Benefit with Him. Shall not the Husband pray, or Hear and Receiv, becauſe the wife of his Boſome is paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and irreconciliable? Shall not <hi>Lot</hi> make haſt out of <hi>Sodome,</hi> becauſe his ſon-in-laws do not prepare to go with him? That it is a Duty to receiv the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is plain enough by that precept, <hi>Do this in Remembrance of mee:</hi> That ther is a Benefit reached forth to us in it, is as evident by that word of our Saviour, <hi>This is my Body, This is my Blood; He that eateth my fleſh, and drinketh my blood, hath everlaſting life.</hi> Nay more: This Benefit cannot be had without this duty: <hi>Except yee eat the fleſh of the Son of man, and drinke his blood, yee have no life in you,</hi> Joh. 6.53. You will perhaps reply: That Duties muſt be performed in a right manner, otherwiſe we may provoke God: Iſrael muſt eat the Paſſover, yet not in their uncleanneſs, nor with the unclean, ſay the ſame of Chriſtians. I grant the Propoſition for ſound and good: The inſtance of Iſrael doth not reach home to the point in hand. It doth not appear by any text of Scripture: That if the Maſter of the familie did neglect to exclude ſuch as were unclean, that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the children or ſervants did, or might lawfully forbear the Paſſover.</p>
                  <p>Add this alſo, To bring home the Argument more particularly to the cauſe in hand where a prepared Heart may comply with the principall end of Receiving the Sacrament, ther ought he not to abſent himſelf for want of the ſecondary, Reaſon giveth it. That wher ther is a Duty to be done, a Benefit to be expected: If ther be divers Ends of doing that duty, ſome more, ſome leſs principall: No reaſon to neglect that by which the Principall end may be obtained, becauſe we cannot obtain th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>condary. Now then, As God hath appointed and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained this Sacrament; 1. To hold forth the Benefit of Chriſts death to the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Receiver, that by partaking of Chriſts fleſh and blood the Chriſtian may be more neerly united to Chriſt himſelf in the firſt place, and then to the members of Chriſt. 2. To call for and cauſe in the Society of the faithfull a publick Teſtification of their mutuall love and charity one to another as members of the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:111276:16"/> ſame myſticall body. So, the principall end of Receiving is to continue the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Communion with Chriſt, and all good Chriſtians (the living members of Chriſt) which was begun in Baptiſm: And the ſecondary is to make profeſſion of it by joining with this and that Aſſembly of Chriſtians. Now then, ſince the primary end of Receiving is our Union with Chriſt: and our union with Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians is but the ſecondary (For we are not united to Chriſt by being received into the Congregation, but indeed received into the Congregation becauſe firſt united to Chriſt.) Nay ſince, the primary end, is Union: and our Profeſſion or Teſtification therof is but the ſecond (or third) end of Receiving. Therfore where the Primary end may be obteined, why ſhould the want of the ſecond (or perhaps the third) be accounted any juſt barr to keep us off. Now, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the mixture of bad with the good, or the ſcandalous courſes of over-many in the Aſſembly might ſeem a juſt barr to our Profeſſion of Communion and Fellowſhip with this or that Congregation, yet ſince it cannot hinder us in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining our deſire of Union with Chriſt, and his myſticall Body, why ſhould this mixture be any barr to the Duty enjoined? In very deed if that Profeſſion of our ſelves to be of the Number of them who hold of Chriſt and his Church, if this (I ſay) were the principall end of Receiving the Sacrament, Then were there ſome ſhew of Reaſon to forbear joining with a mixt Aſſembly: But now it is otherwiſe. It were indeed to be wiſhed that the whole Congregation were ſuch as that we might affectionatly deſire to continue in Communion and Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with them: But if it fall out otherwiſe through the fault of other men: Can that be a ſufficient reaſon to hinder us from the Sacrament; The prime fruit and Benefit wher-of we may partake of, even in the mixt Aſſembly? Add this alſo: That it is charitably ſuppoſed, ther be ſome Saints in the Congregation; and in our addreſs to the Sacrament we do profeſs our deſire of Union and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with them: if others intrude themſelves, we came not thither to meet with them. Now the Queſtion is, whether we may neglect the good and godly Chriſtians, and that Duty which we ow to God in reſpect of them, becauſe of the bad and wicked, whom finding ther, we have not power to remove.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="argument">
                  <head>The third Argument.</head>
                  <p>TThat Opinion which in the beſt Ages of the Church hath been condemned of errour: And that which neceſſarily caſteth Chriſtians upon inextricable difficulty's and diſcomforts, is in all probability erroneous, and therfore not to be embraced: Such is the opinion of them who hold it ſinfull for a Chriſtian (tho well-prepared for the holy Sacrament by ſelf-examination according to the Doctrine of the Apoſtle) to draw neer to the Table of the Lord in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of them that are unjuſtly permitted to come to that holy Ordinance, That it hath been condemned as erroneous in the beſt ages of the Church, is
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:111276:17"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:111276:17"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:111276:18"/> evident by the ſtory of the Novatians firſt, and the Donatiſts afterward, who upon ſuch grounds made a ſeparation from the Church of God,<note place="margin">Againſt the Donatiſts doth St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> diſpute, as did St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> before him againſt the Novatians. Note here, that often in his books <hi>De Bapt. contra Donatist, &amp; contra Creſcon, Gram. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 15. doth St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> cite an Authority out of <hi>Cyprian, lib de lapſis,</hi> to prove the concluſion that we have in hand. <hi>Nos non communicare peccatis aliorum etiamſi cum iis in Sacramentorum com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munione maneamus.</hi>
                     </note> and ſet up ſelect Congregations of their own; utterly condemning thoſe Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and Aſſemblies, who admitted of any ſuch to the Communion of the Church whom they accounted fit to be ſuſpended from the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the ſociety of the faithfull.</p>
                  <p>That it doth neceſſarily caſt many Chriſtians upon inextricable difficulties and diſcomforts is evident in this: That if it be unlawfull to receiv the Sacramant in a mixt Aſſembly; Then it may fall out that ſome Chriſtians may for ever be deprived of that Ordinance, and ſo want that comfort both in life and death, which they might have by it. For why? ſome have not liberty nor means of ſeparation, and ſeeking elſewhere, <hi>ex. gr.</hi> Wives, children, ſervants which are under the Covert and command of their Husbands, Parents, Maſters: Some again are ſhut up in priſon; others baniſhed or confined to ſuch a place where this Doctrine is not beleeved, nor is that Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment any where to be had, but in the Parochiall Aſſemblies of that Place and People. Now for all ſuch to be deprived of the Sacrament, and of the comfort which cometh by it, is a matter of ſuch inconvenience, that it cannot in any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability be allowed as an Order, and Appointment of Chriſt. Conſequently I conclude; That the Opinion which denyeth it lawfull for a Chriſtian to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate in a mixt Aſſembly, is in all probability erroneous and not to be received.</p>
                  <p>This alſo may be caſt in to make up full weight and meaſure: That we find in the Goſpel our Bleſſed Saviour not excluding <hi>Iudas</hi> from the Paſſover, even when he knew that he had conſpired with the Prieſts to betray him. Nor do any of the Diſciples, when our Saviour told them, <hi>Yee are not all clean, One of you ſhall betray me,</hi> not any of them do call upon Chriſt to turn out the Traitour, no not when by the Sopp given to <hi>Judas,</hi> Chriſt had manifeſted him to be the man. Wher-in if the Apoſtles were to blame (ſo it may be theſe men may think) as not ſufficiently (at that time) carefull to have an Holy Communion by ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the pretious from the vile: yet certainly our bleſſed Saviour did not at all tranſgreſs the Rule of Holineſs, Nor would he have permitted <hi>Iudas</hi> to ſit ſo neer them, if any of them might therby fail of Receiving the Benefit that might upon ſelf-preparation be juſtly expected from that Sacrament. Nor do I know what can be excepted againſt this, unleſs any would deny the Neceſſity of morall cleanneſs to the preparing and fitting of the Jews for the worthy receiving of the Paſſover, or boldly avouch that nothing more was required of them but a care
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:111276:18"/> of Ceremoniall purity, and legall purifications of the Fleſh: which I ſuppoſe is an opinion ſo groſs and abſurd, that none of underſtanding would own it and avouch it. We read <hi>Hezekiah</hi> urging the Preparation of the Heart, as an Argument to prevail with God to pardon the neglect of Ceremoniall purifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: which had been of no force at all, if thoſe Purifications had not been required only in the way of ſignification and commonefaction to put them in mind of that ſpirituall and morall duty, the Preparation of Heart. If God took any pleaſure in waſhing the hands, and ſcouring the fleſh, why doth our Saviour blame the Phariſees who were but too diligent, and obſervant of their Ceremonies: No, no: Evident it is, that Sacrifices and Ceremonies, were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable only as Inſtitutions, and Admonitions of Morall Duties: As at other times; So in their Preparation of themſelves to the Holy Sacrament: Nor was it enough for <hi>Iudas</hi> that he was clean (as farr as the water could reach) no not enough that his feet were waſhed (if waſhed they were) by Chriſt: Since the Heart was full of covetouſnes and diveliſh intentions. Whoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, might it be an hinderance to the Reſidue in receiving the Benefit of the Sacrament, Can we with reaſon beleev, that our Saviour would not have ſhutt him out, and ſo have taught them (upon ſuch an occaſion) the Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of what theſe men call for with ſo much importunity?</p>
                  <p>I cloſe up all in a word: Since neither Scripture nor Reaſon do conclude it unlawfull. Nay ſince (the Scripture being ſilent in the cauſe, neither prohibiting nor reprehending) Reaſon doth draw us to conclude againſt the opinion of theſe men: I conclude, <hi>It is not ſinfull for a Chriſtian to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv the Sacrament in a mixt Aſſembly.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Appendix.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Extracted out of a Reſponſary Letter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To your two Queſtions propounded in the cloſe of the Letter I return this breef Anſwer for your ſatisfaction.</p>
                  <p>To the firſt <hi>viz. Whether it be not a ſinn in the Miniſter to deliver the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to him that is ſcandalous: i. e.</hi> to him who having been ſuch, hath not as yet reconciled himſelf to God and the Church by publik evidences of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. I cannot admit the Affirmative for a Truth, <hi>viz.</hi> It is ſin in him ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept with theſe limitations.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. When ther is power in the Hand of the Miniſter to keep ſuch men off, and to bring them to the Teſtification of their Repentance. 2. Where it is evident
<pb facs="tcp:111276:19"/> to the Miniſter, that the man hath not reconciled himſelf to God and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation. 3. When the man is indeed ſcandalous <hi>i. e.</hi> notoriouſly known to have given offence. But the caſe is otherwiſe; when either the Miniſter hath not power in his hand: or when he is not certain of the Mans Non-Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and Non-Reconciliation: Or thirdly, when the man is not indeed ſcandalous. I ſay, <hi>Not indeed,</hi> Becauſe ſome men account ſome things to be ſcandalous which indeed are not. Ther is a ſcandal to a weak brother in the want of a charitable uſe of Chriſtian Liberty; Ther is a ſcandal to them that are without: This latter is only that ſcandal that deſerveth repulſe from the Communion: Not the other.</p>
                  <p>To the ſecond <hi>viz, Whether it be not a ſinn in the People to communicate with any ſuch: i. e.</hi> To receiv the Communion in the Society of ſuch a Miniſter, and ſuch a ſcandalous Brother. I ſay as before: I cannot affirm it ſinfull; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept with theſe limitations. 1. When it is evident to the Chriſtian that ſuch a perſon is indeed ſcandalous, and hath not reconciled himſelf. 2. When it is in the liberty of the Communicant to chuſe or refuſe ſuch company. But the caſe is otherwiſe; when it is not evident to him, that the other hath not reconciled himſelf: or when it is not in the liberty of the Comunicant to refuſe. Now as it is not in the liberty of the Chriſtian (ſaving the Duty that he oweth to God) to abſtein altogether from the Sacrament: So neither is it in his liberty (ſaving his duty that he oweth to the Magiſtrat) to abſtain from that Congregation wher-of by vertue of his houſe and Habitation he is known to be a Member. At the Communion of the ſick peradventure he may forbear from joining in ſociety with ſuch, if they ſhould deſire: Not ſo, from the publick Congregation.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>CHARLES HERLE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
